Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
计算机程序的构造和解释
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
翻译&&时间轴
张大伟
（DreamAndDead）
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
计算对象
PROFESSOR: Well, now that we've given you some power
现在我们已经学习了
to make independent local state and to model objects,
如何创建局部状态和如何建模对象
I thought we'd do a bit of programming of a very complicated kind,
我想我们应该找点复杂的东西
just to illustrate what you can do with this sort of thing.
来实践一下学过的这些知识
I suppose, as I said, we were motivated by physical systems
我可以这么说 假设我们处在现实世界中
the ways we like to think about physical systems,
我们把这个世界看作是
which is that there are these things that the world is made out of.
由许多的事物构成的
And each of these things has particular independent local state,
每个事物都有其独立的局部状态
and therefore it is a thing. That's what makes it a thing.
正是这些独立的状态使其成为事物
And then we're going to say that in the model in the world
因此我们说 在这个世界的模型中
we have a world and a model in our minds and in the computer of that world.
我们在大脑中和计算机中对那个世界建模
And what I want to make is a correspondence
我想要建立一种对应关系
between the objects in the world and the objects in the computer,
把现实世界和计算机中的对象联系起来
the relationships between the objects in the world
把现实世界中对象间的关系
and the relationships between those same obj...--the model objects in the computer,
与计算机中的模型对象间的关系 对应起来
and the functions that relate things in the
把现实世界中关联对象的函数
to the functions that relate things in the computer.
与计算机中的函数 对应起来
This buys us modularity.
这让我们获得了模块性
If we really believe the world is like that,
如果我们认为现实世界是像那样的
that it's made out of these little pieces,
也就是由许多小的事物构成的
and of course we could arrange our world to be like that,
当然 我们可以把世界安排成那样
we could only model those things that are like that,
我们只能对像那样的事物建模
then we can inherit the modularity in the world into our programming.
这样 我们的程序就可以从现实世界中继承模块化
That's why we would invent some of this object-oriented programming.
这就是发明面向对象编程的初衷
Well, let's take the best kind of objects I know.
我所见过的最完美的对象（系统）
They're completely--they're completely wonderful: electrical systems.
电气系统 就是非常非常完美的对象系统
Electrical systems really are the physicist's best, best objects.
电气系统真的是物理学家构造的非常非常好的一种对象
You see over here I have some piece of machinery.
这里 我有一些机器零件
Right here's a piece of machinery.
就是这些零件
And it's got an electrical wire connecting
有一个电线连接起了
one part of the machinery with another part of the machinery.
零件的两个部分
And one of the wonderful properties of the electrical world
电气世界中 有一个非常棒的特性
is that I can say this is an object,
就是我可以说这是一个对象
and this is an object,
这又是一个对象
and they're-- the connection between them is clear.
它们间的关联一目了然
In principle, there is no connection that I didn't describe with these wires.
而且 如果我没有用电线连接 它们便没有关联
Let's say if I have light bulbs,
比如我有一个灯泡
Let's say if I have light bulbs, a light bulb and a power supply that's plugged into the outlet.
一个灯泡和一个已经接在插座上的电源
Then the connection is perfectly clear.
关联非常明了
There's no other connections that we know of.
这就是已知所有的连接方式了
If I were to tie a knot in the wire that connects the light bulb to the power supply,
就算我把连接电灯和电源的电线打个结
the light remains lit up.
灯仍然是亮的
It doesn't care.
没什么影响
That the way the physics is arranged is such that the connection can be made abstract,
物理学上这样安排 可以使连接变成抽象的
at least for low frequencies and things like that.
至少在低频状态下是可以的
So in fact, we have captured all of the connections there really are.
而且这就是全部的关联方式了
Well, as you can go one step further
当然 我们来进一步
and talk about the most abstract types of electrical systems we have,
讨论一种在电气系统中最为广泛的抽象
digital to dual circuits.
数字电路
And here there are certain kinds of objects.
这里有一些对象
For example, in digital circuits we have things like inverters.
例如 在数字电路里中 我们有非门
We have things like and-gates.
有与门
We have things like or-gates.
还有或门
We connect them together by sort-of wires
我们用一种特殊的“电线” 把它们连接起来
which represent abstract signals.
这些“电线”代表抽象信号
We don't really care as physical variables
我们不关心具体的物理因素
whether these are voltages or currents or some combination
像电压、电流或者组合因素等
or water, water pressure.
又或者是水压 等等
These abstract variables represent certain signals.
这些抽象变量代表某类信号
And we build systems by wiring these things together with wires.
我们用电路连接元件 构建系统
So today what I'm going to show you, right now,
现在 我要向你们介绍一门新的语言
we're going to build up an invented language in Lisp,
我们要构建一门内嵌于Lisp中的语言
embedded in the same sense that Henderson's picture language was embedded,
这是一种内部DSL 是类似于之前讲过的图形语言那种
which is not the same sense
而不是昨天那种
as the language of pattern match and substitution was done yesterday.
那种模式匹配语言 -- 那是外部DSL
The pattern match substitution language was interpreted by a Lisp program.
模式匹配语言是由Lisp程序所解释的
But the embedding of Henderson's program
而之前那种图形语言
is that we just build up more and more procedures that encapsulate the structure we want.
是在Lisp中构造我们想要的过程 来封装图形结构
So for example here,
举例来说
I'm going to have some various primitive kinds of objects, as you see,
首先我要有一些基本对象
that one and that one.
比如这个和这个
I'm going to use wires to combine them.
然后用电线去组合它们
The way I represent attaching-- I can make wires.
我用(MAKE-WIRE)来构造一个电线
So let's say A is a wire.
A就代表了一根电线
And B is a wire.
B也是
And C is a wire.
C也是
And D is a wire.
D也是
And E is wire.
还有E
And S is a wire.
S也是
Well, an or-gate that has both inputs, the inputs being A and B,
而或门有两个输入 分别是A和B
and the output being wire D,
它的输出是D
you notate like this.
我们用这样的记号来表示
An and-gate, which has inputs A and B and output C,
与门 输入是A和B 输出是C
we notate like that.
我们这样表示
By making such a sequence of declarations,
通过一系列像这样的声明
I can wire together an arbitrary circuit.
我可以组合出任意的电路
So I've just told you a set of primitives
我已经告诉了你们创建数字电路
and means of combination for building digital circuits,
的基本元素和组合方法了
when I need more in a real language than abstraction.
然后就该说抽象的方法了
And so for example, here I have--here I have a half adder.
举例来说 这是一个半加器
It's something you all know if you've done any digital design.
如果你学过电路设计肯定知道这个东西
It's used for adding numbers together on A and B
输入两个数A和B
and putting out a sum and a carry.
输出两者之和以及进位
And in fact, the wiring diagram is exactly what I told you.
事实上 完全可以用我刚刚说的来组合电路
A half adder with things that come out of the box--
盒子外面 半加器盒子的外面有一些接口
you see the box, the boundary, the abstraction is always a box.
这些盒子的边界 我们总是抽象成盒子
And there are things that come out of it, A, B, S, and C.
从盒子里引出A、B、S、C四根线
Those are the declared variables--
这些是已经声明了的变量
declared variables of a lambda expression,
由LAMBDA表达式声明的几个变量
which is the one that defines half adder.
定义了这个半加器
And internal to that, I make up some more wires, D and E,
在盒子的内部 我构造了电线D和E
which I'm going to use for the interconnect--
这是为了连接内部结构
here E is this one and D is this wire,
这条是E 这条是D
the interconnect that doesn't come through the walls of the box--
内部连接的线路并没有引出盒子之外
and wire things together as you just saw.
就像电路图那样连起来
And the nice thing about this that I've just shown you
大家可以看得出来
this language is hierarchical in the right way.
这个语言非常有层次性
If a language isn't hierarchical in the right way,
如果一门语言没有层次性
if it turns out that a compound object doesn't look like a primitive,
如果你不能把一个复合对象当成基本对象来使用
there's something wrong with the language--
这门语言肯定是有问题的
at least the way I feel about that.
至少我是这么认为的
So here we have--here, instead of starting with mathematical functions,
之前 我们都是在研究数学函数
or things that compute mathematical functions,
或者是计算数学函数的东西
which is what we've been doing up until now,
这些都是我们之前研究的东西
instead of starting with things that look like mathematical functions,
而我们现在
or compute such things,
不这么做了
we are starting with things that are electrical objects
我们从一些电气对象开始
and we build up more electrical objects.
构建更多的对象
And the glue we're using is basically the Lisp structure: lambdas.
我们用Lisp里的LAMBDA将其粘合起来
Lambda is the ultimate glue, if you will.
“LAMBDA: 终极之粘合剂”
And of course, half adder itself can be used
当然 半加器可以用于
in a more complicated abstraction called a full adder,
构造一种更复杂的抽象结构 -- 全加器
which in fact involves two half adders, as you see here,
如这里所示 全加器由两个半加器构成
hooked together with some extra wires,
用一些额外的电线连接起来
that you see here, S, C1, and C2, and an or-gate,
就像这里所示的S、C1、C2以及一个或门
to manufacture a full adder,
而对于一个全加器
which takes a input number, another input number, a carry in,
它的输入有：两个待加的数 一个进位值
and produces output, a sum and a carry out.
输出是：两数之和以及进位
And out of full adders, you can make real adder chains and big adders.
构建好全加器以后 还可以把它们链起来组成更大的加法器
So we have here a language so far
现在我们有了一门完整的语言
That has primitives, means of combination, and means of abstraction to real language.
它有基本元素、组合方法以及抽象方法
Now, how are we going to implement this?
现在 我们怎样实现这门语言？
Well, let's do it easily.
其实并不难
Let's look at the primitives.
首先来看基本元素
The only problem is we have to implement the primitives.
这是唯一的问题
Nothing else has to be implemented,
不需要再做其它事情了
because we're picking up the means of combination and abstraction from Lisp,
因为我们直接借用了Lisp中的组合方法以及抽象方法
inheriting them in the embedding.
我们的语言 继承自Lisp并内嵌于其中
OK, so let's look at a particular primitive.
好 我们先来看一个基本元素
An inverter is a nice one.
就拿非门来说吧
Now, inverter has two wires coming in, an in and an out.
非门有两个引脚 分别是输入和输出
And somehow, it's going to have to know what to do when a signal comes in.
它要对输入信号做出响应
So somehow it's going to have to tell its input wire--
它需要对输入电线说 --
and now we're going to talk about objects
我们现在把它们视作对象
and we're going to see this in a little more detail soon--
其具体细节我们稍后讨论
but it's going to have to tell its input wire
它对其输入电线的说
that when you change, tell me.
“当你的值变发生改变时 告诉我一声”
So this object, the object which is the inverter
所以非门这个对象
has to tell the object which is the input wire,
会对输入电线这个对象说 --
hi, my name is George.
“Hi 我是George”
And my, my job is to do something with results when you change.
“我的工作就是 对你的变化做出响应”
So when you change, you get a change, tell me about it.
“所以当你变化的时候 告诉我一声”
Because I've got to do something with that.
“这样我才能进一步的处理”
Well, that's done down here by adding an action on the input wire called invert-in,
这是通过在这里 在输入电线上
添加一个叫做INVERT-IN的动作来实现的
where invert-in is defined over here
INVERT-IN在这里定义
to be a procedure of no arguments,
它是一个无参过程
which gets the logical not of the signal on the input wire.
它将线路上的信号逻辑取反
And after some delay, which is the inverter delay,
经过一段时长为INVERTER-DELAT的延时以后 --
all these electrical objects have delays,
每个电路对象都有延时 --
we'll do the following thing--
然后我们会 --
set the signal on the output wire to the new value.
我们再把输出设置为新的值
A very simple program.
非常简单
Now, you have to imagine that the output wire has to be sensitive
你可以想象输出电线也同样是信号敏感的
and know that when its signal changes,
当信号改变的时候
it may have to tell other guys,
它会“告知”其它对象
Hi, wake up. My value has changed.
“快醒醒！我的值已经改变啦”
So when you hook together inverter with an and-gate or something like that,
所以当你把非门和与门或者元件连在一起的时候
there has to be a lot of communication going on
它们之间将会有大量的通信
to make sure that the signal propagates right.
以确保信号正确地传播
And down here is nothing very exciting.
到目前为止 没什么新奇的东西
This is just the definition of logical not
我们只是针对某个特定的表示法
for some particular representations of the logical values-- 1, 0 in this case.
也就是这个例子中的1、0 -- 实现了LOGICAL-NOT而已
And we can look at things more complicated like and-gates.
与门就相对复杂一些
And-gates take two inputs, A1 and A2, we'll call them, and produce an output.
与门有两个输入A1和A2 输出是OUTPUT
But the structure of the and-gate is identical to the one we just saw.
但是其结构和非门没有什么大的不同
There's one called an and-action procedure that's defined,
只不过是 当输入信号改变的时候
which is the thing that gets called when an input is changed.
与门调用的是AND-ACTION过程罢了
And what it does, of course, is nothing more than
当然 它所做的只是
compute the logical and of the signals on the inputs.
对输入信号进行逻辑“与”运算
And after some delay, called the and-gate-delay,
在经过AND-GATE-DELAY的延时之后
calls this procedure, which sets a signal on the output to a new value.
调用这个过程 更新输出信号值
Now, how I implement these things is all wishful thinking.
那么 我们如何用“按愿望思维”来构造这一切呢？
As you see here, I have an assignment operation.
如大家所见 这里有一个赋值运算
It's not set.
但并不是SET!
It's a derived assignment operation in the same way
这是一个派生出来的运算
we had functions that were derived from CAR and CDR.
就像可以从CAR和CDR派生出其它函数一样
So I, by convention, label that with an exclamation point.
因此 按照约定 我加上“!”（表示这个过程有副作用）
And over here, you see there's an add-action!,
这里有个过程ADD-ACTION!
which is to inform the wire, called A1 locally in this and-gate,
它用来提醒与门中的局部线路A1
to call the and-action-procedure when it gets changed,
当它改变的时候记得执行过程AND-ACTION-PROCEDURE
and the wire A2 to call the and-action procedure when it gets changed.
A2也是一样
All very simple.
非常简单
Well, let's talk a little bit about this communication
现在我们再来看看
that must occur between these various parts.
各部分间是如何通信的
Suppose, for example,
例如
I have a very simple circuit
有一个非常简单的电路
which contains and-gate with wires a and b.
它有一个与门 带有两个输入A、B
And that connects through a wire called c to an inverter
与门通过电线C跟非门相连
which has a wire output called d.
非门的输出是D
What are the comput...--here's the physical world.
这就是物理世界
It's an abstraction of the physical world.
一个对物理世界的抽象
Now I can buy these out of little pieces that you get at Radio Shack for a few cents.
要不了几分钱就可以从Radio Shack买到这些元件
And there are boxes that act like this,
那些元件的作用和画在这里的差不多
which have little numbers on them like LS04 or something.
元件上都标有类似于LS04的标签
Now supposing I were to try to say what's the computational model.
现在来看其中的计算模型
What is the thing that corresponds to that,
它又对应着什么
that part of reality in the mind of us and in the computer?
计算机中的对象对应着我们思维中的什么
Well, I have to assign for every object in the world an object in the computer,
我需要把现实世界中的每个对象与计算机中的对应起来
and for every relationship in the world between them a relationship in the computer.
把两个世界中对象之间的关系也对应起来
That's my goal.
这是我的目标
So let's do that.
让我们来看看怎么做
Well, I have some sort of thing called the signal, A.
这一团东西代表信号A
This is A. It's a signal.
这是信号A
It's a cloudy thing like that.
画得像一团云
And I have another one down here which I'm going to call B.
再画另一个信号 -- B
It's another signal.
它是另一个信号
Now this signal--these two signals
这两个信号
are somehow going to have to hook together
要通过某种方式连在一起
into a box, let's call it this, which is the and-gate, action procedure.
连在这个盒子上 -- 这就代表与门
That's the and-gate's action procedure.
这就是与门的动作过程
And it's going to produce
它将产生
well, it's going to interact with a signal object, which we call C--
它将与另外一个称作C的信号对象交互
a wire object, excuse me, we call C.
哦 说错了 是一条电线C
this is going to put out again, or connect to, another action procedure
这跟电线 又将连在另一个动作过程上
which is one associated with the inverter in the world, not.
在我们的电气世界中 这个过程跟一个非门关联
And I'm going to have another--another wire, which we'll call D.
我还有另外一根电线 -- D
So here's my layout of stuff.
整体布局就是这样
Now we have to say what's inside them and what they have to know to compute.
现在必须来研究它们 有关计算的内部机制了
Well, every--every one of these wires has to know
每一跟电线都必须知道
what the value of the signal that's on that wire is.
自己承载的信号是什么
So there's going to be some variable inside here, we'll call it signal.
我们用变量SIGNAL来表示
And he owns a value.
SIGNAL的值就是信号
So there must be some environment associated with this.
也不要忘了它所关联的环境
And for each one of these, there must be an environment that binds signal.
对于每个元件来说 一定有一个环境绑定了信号
And there must be a signal here, therefore.
因此 这里也有一个SIGNAL变量
And presumably, signal's a value that's either 1 or 0,
SIGNAL的值不是0就是1
and signal.
这儿也有个SIGNAL
Now, we also have to have some
现在 一旦这里的信号改变
list of people to inform if the signal here changes.
我们需要通知一系列的对象
We're going to have to inform this.
我们得通知这个与门
So I've got that list. We'll call it the Action Procedures, AP.
这里有个表 我们把它叫做AP
And it's presumably a list.
它可能是一个表
But the first thing on the list, in this case, is this guy.
在本例中 表里面的第一项条目是这个东西
And the action procedures of this one happens to have some list of stuff.
这个元件也有一个称为AP的表
There might be other people who are sharing A, who are looking at it.
也可能有一些其它对象 时刻等待着A来通知“它们”
So there might be other guys on this list, like
所以这里可能有其它对象 比如
like somebody over there that we don't know about.
一些其它我们不知道的对象
It's the other guy attached to A.
这些是与A连接的其它对象
And the action procedure here also has to point to that,
这里的AP表
the list of action procedures.
也指向这个与门
And of course, that means this one, its action procedures
相类似的 这里的AP表
has to point up to here.
也要指向这里
This is the things-- the people it has to inform.
这里是C要通知的元件
And this guy has some too.
D也一样
But I don't know what they are
但是我不知道它要通知谁
because I didn't draw it in my diagram.
因为我的图中没有画出来
It's the things connected to D.
可能是和D连接起来的其它元件
Now, it's also the case
同样的
that when the and-action procedure is awakened,
当AND-ACTION过程被唤醒时
saying one of the people who know that you've told
也就是说 之前你拜托某人将你唤醒
one of the people you've told to wake you up if their signal changes,
你拜托它们 当它们的信号发生改变时通知你
you have to go look and ask them what's their signal
你得去检查它的信号是什么
so you can do the and, and produce a signal for this one.
这样你就可以计算逻辑与 输出信号给下一个元件
So there has to be, for example,
所里 这里就必须要有
information here saying A1, my A1 is this guy,
有信息说 A1是这个元件
my A1 is this guy, and my A2 is this guy.
A2就是这个元件
And not only that,
不只是这样
when I do my and, I'm going to have to tell this guy something.
当我在计算逻辑与时 我还得告诉这个元件一些信息
So I need an output--  being this guy.
还有一个输出 输出给这个元件
And similarly, this guy's going to have a thing called the input
同样地 非门也有一个输入
that he interrogates to find out
当信号被唤醒并告知它信号被修改时
what the value of the signal on the input is,
非门会询问该信号
when the signal wakes up and says, I've changed,
你的值是什么
and sends a message this way saying, I've changed.
信号通过像这样发消息 告知“信号已改变”
This guy says, OK, what's your value now?
它就反过来查询这个新的信号值
When he gets that value, then he's going to have to say,
取到值之后 它将会
OK, output changes this guy, changes this guy.
计算输出 并改变这个信号的值
And so on.
以此类推
And so I have to have at least that much connected-ness.
因此我也必须有这么多的连接
Now, let's go back and look, for example, at the and-gate.
现在我们回头观察一下 这个与门
Here we are back on this slide.
回到这张幻灯片
And we can see some of these parts.
这几个部分的内容
For any particular and-gate, there is an A1, there is an A2, and the output.
对每个与门 都有A1、A2两个输入 一个OUTPUT输出
And those are, those are
这些都是
an environment that was created at the--those produce a frame
在AND-GATE被调用时的环境中
at the time and-gate was called,
这些参数创建了一个框架
A frame where A1, A2, and output are--
这个框架用来存放A1、A2和OUTPUT的值
have as their values, they're bound to
它们都要与电线相绑定
the wires which, they are--which were passed in.
这些电线就是通过参数传进来的
In that environment,
在这个环境下
I constructed a procedure
我构建一个过程
this one right there.
就在这里
And-action-procedure was constructed in that environment.
在该环境下定义的AND-ACTION-PROCEDURE
That was the result of evaluating a lambda expression.
这个实际上是对一个LAMBDA表达式求值
So it hangs onto the frame where these were defined.
它跟求值该LAMBDA表达式时的环境相绑定
Local--part of its local state is that.
找到它的局部环境
The and-action-procedure, therefore, has
因此AND-ACTION-PROCEDURE过程能够
access to A1, A2, and output as we see here.
存取这里看到的A1、A2和OUTPUT
A1, A2, and output.
A1、A2、OUTPUT
Now, we haven't looked inside of a wire yet.
我们还没有深入探索“电线”的内部结构
That's all that remains.
那是仅剩的部分
Let's look at a wire.
来看看“电线”
Like the overhead, very good.
麻烦请开一下投影仪
Well, the wire, again, is a, is a somewhat complicated mess.
“电线”是有那么一点复杂
Ooh, wrong one.
哦 摁错了
It's a big complicated mess, like that.
是非常复杂 像这样
But let's look at it in detail and see what's going on.
但是还是来看一下 到底是什么
Well, the wire is one of these.
“电线”是这样的一种东西
And it has to have two things that are part of it, that it's state.
有两个主要部分 都是它的状态
One of them is the signal we see here.
我们这里看到的 一个是信号值
Heres, when we call make-wire to make a wire,
这里 当我们调用MAKE-WIRE创建一条电线时
then the first thing we do is we create some variables
我们首先要创建一些变量
which are the signal
分别是这条电线的
and the action procedures for this wire.
SIGNAL和ACTION-PROCS
And in that context,
在这个上下文中
we define various functions--or procedures, excuse me, procedures.
我们定义了一系列的过程
One of them is called set-my-signal to a new value.
其中一个是(SET-MY-SIGNAL! NEW)
And what that does is takes a new value in.
它所做的只是 取一个新值NEW
If that's equal to my current value of my signal, I'm done.
如果NEW和SIGNAL一样 信号没有变化 就没必要做什么了
Otherwise, I set the signal to the new value
否则 把SIGNAL的值赋值为NEW
and call each of the action procedures
再调用ACTION-PROCS里的所有过程
that I've been, that I've been--what's the right word? --  introduced to.
那些我之前引入的过程
I get introduced when the and-gate was applied to me.
也就是我在定义与门时就定义的过程
By add action procedure at the bottom.
是在代码最后调用ADD-ACTION-PROCEDURE实现的
Also, I have to define a way of accepting an action procedure--
然后 我还得定义一个过程 用来接受动作
which is what you see here---
也就是这段代码
which increments my action procedures
它增加了AP表
using set to the result of CONSing up a new process--a procedure,
这是通过使用SET!将PROC与旧的AP表CONS起来实现的
which is passed to me, on to my actions procedures list.
而这个PROC是作为参数传递进来的
And for technical reasons, I have to call that procedure one.
由于技术原因 最后还要再运行一次PROC
So I'm not going to tell you anything about that,
我不会再对此详细展开
that has to do with event-driven simulations and getting them started,
这是一种事件驱动的模拟
which takes a little bit of thinking.
要想把这个讲清楚还是得花点时间
And finally, I'm going to define a thing called the dispatcher,
最后 我还要定义一个“分派器”
which is a way of passing a message to a wire,
这是一种将消息分派给电线的方法
which is going to be used to extract from it various information,
它将用于从中抽取出不同的信息
like what is the current signal value?
比如这里 当前的信号值是多少？
What is the method of setting your signal?
设置新信号值的方法是什么？
I want to get that out of it.
我想要这个方法
How do I--how do I add another action procedure?
我怎么样去添加另外的动作过程呢？
And I'm going to return that dispatch, that procedure as a value.
最后 以DISPATCH过程为返回值返回
So the wire that I've constructed
因此 我所构造的电线
is a message accepting object
是一种可以接收消息的对象
which accepts a message like, like
它接收的消息类似于
what's your method of adding action procedures?
“你的哪个方法可以用来添加动作过程？”
That it'll give me a procedure,
它返回一个过程
which is the add action procedure,
它返回ADD-ACTION-PROCUDURE
which I can then apply to an action procedure
我可以将其应用在一个动作过程上
to create another action procedure in the wire.
从而实现将一个动作过程加入电线的AP表中
So that's a permission.
这是一种“许可”
So it's given me permission to change your action procedures.
使得你可以去修改自身的AP表
And in fact, you can see that over here.
实际上 你可以在这里看到
Next slide.
下一张幻灯片
Ah.
噢
This is nothing very interesting.
没什么有意思的
The call each of the action procedures
CALL-EACH调用每个动作过程
is just a CDRing down a list.
这只是对一个表不断做CDR
And I'm not going to even talk about that anymore.
没什么好说的
We're too advanced for that.
我们早就知道了
However, if I want to get a signal from a wire,
然而 如果我想知道线路上的信号值
I ask the wire-- which is,
我询问该线路：你的 --
what is the wire?
回想一下 什么是线路？
The wire is the dispatch returned by creating the wire.
线路对象只是在创建它时所返回的分派过程而已
It's a procedure.
只是一个过程
I call that dispatch on the message get-signal.
我向该分派器发送一个消息'GET-SIGNAL
And what I should expect to get is a method of getting a signal.
实际得到的是一个方法 用于取得线路信号值
Or actually, I get the signal.
进一步 我就可以得到信号值
If I want to set a signal,
如果我想要设置一个信号值
I want to change a signal,
我想要改变一个信号值
then what I'm going to do
我要做的是
is take a wire as an argument and a new value for the signal,
以一个线路和信号的新值作为参数
I would ask the wire for permission to set the signal
我向线路请求许可 来设置它的信号值
and use that permission, which is a procedure, on the new value.
我会用该许可 -- 也就是一个过程 -- 应用在一个新值上
And if we go back to the overhead here,
我们再过来看投影
Okay, thank you,
好的 谢谢
we go back to the overhead here,
我们看这里的投影
we see that the method-- if I ask for the method of setting the signal,
我们看到 如果我请求设置信号的方法
that's over here,
也就是这段代码
it's set-my-signal, a procedure that's defined inside the wire,
返回的是一个定义在线路内部的SET-MY-SIGNAL!方法
which if we look over here
回过头来看它的定义
is the thing that says
它的定义是
set my internal value called the signal,
将我的一个内部变量SIGNAL的值设为
my internal variable, which is the signal,
这个内部变量 用于存储信号值
to the new value, which is passed to me as an argument,
将其值设为通过参数传递的NEW
and then call each of the action procedures waking them up.
然后调用AP表中的过程 来唤醒它们
Very simple.
非常简单
Ok, Going back to that slide,
回头来看刚才的幻灯片
we also have the one last thing--
还有最后一点
which I suppose now you can easily work out for yourself--
我想你们现在应该很轻易地就能理解了
is the way you add an action.
关于我们如何添加新的动作过程
You take a wire--a wire and an action procedure.
我们需要WIRE和ACTION-PROC两个参数
And I ask the wire for permission to add an action.
然后请求添加动作过程的许可
Getting that permission, I use that permission to give it an action procedure.
得到许可后 用该许可去添加新的动作过程
So that's a real object.
所以 这确实是一个“对象”
There's a few more details about this.
还有些细节
For example, how am I going to control this thing?
比如 我怎么来控制它？
How do I do these delays?
这些延时怎么实现？
Okay? Let's look at that for a second.
我们来快速过一遍
The next one here.
下一张
Let's see.
我们来看看
We know when we looked at the and-gate or the not-gate
我们细看与门、或门的定义
that when a signal changed on the input,
会发现当输入信号改变时
there was a delay.
会有“延时”
And then it was going to call the procedure,
然后它将调用过程
which was going to change the output.
来改变输出
Well, how are we going to do this?
这个要如何实现？
We're going to make up some mechanism,
我们将要建立一种机制
a fairly complicated mechanism at that,
一种相当复杂的机制
which we're going to have to be very careful about.
我们得非常细心地来看
But after a delay, we're going to do an action.
一段延时之后 我们将执行一个动作
A delay is a number,
DELAY是一个数
and an action is a procedure.
而ACTION是一个过程
What that's going to be is they're going to have a special structure called an agenda,
我们引入一种称为THE-AGENDA的特殊数据结构
which is a thing that organizes time and actions.
用于组织时间与动作
And we're going to see that in a while.
一会儿再来仔细研究
I don't want to get into that right now.
先把这里说完
But the agenda has a moment at which--at which something happens.
THE-AGENDA将记录执行动作的时刻
We're setting up for later at some moment,
我们把它设定在未来的某个时刻
which is the sum of the time, which is the delay time plus the current time,
也就是在CURRENT-TIME加上DELAT的时刻
which the agenda thinks is now.
触发关联的动作
We're going to set up to do this action,
我们把准备好要执行的动作
and add that to the agenda.
添加入THE-AGENDA中
And the way this machine will now run is very simple.
要使这个“机器”运行起来并不困难
We have a thing called propagate, which is the way things run.
我们利用这个PROPAGATE过程来完成这件事
If the agenda is empty, we're done--if there's nothing more to be done.
如果THE-AGENDA为空 就没有要做的
Otherwise,
否则
we're going to take the first item off the agenda,
我们就取出THE-AGENDA的第一个元素
and that's a procedure of no arguments.
它是一个无参过程
So that we're going to see extra parentheses here.
所以这里有额外的括号
We call that on no arguments.
我们对其进行无参调用
That takes the action.
这就执行了之前存入的动作
Then we remove that first item from the agenda,
然后我们从THE-AGENDA中删除第一个元素
and we go around the propagation loop.
然后再进入传播循环
So that's the overall structure of this thing.
这就是整体的结构
Now, there's a, a few other things we can look at.
还有点其它的
And then we're going to look into the agenda a little while from now.
现在 我们来看看THE-AGENDA的内部结构
Now the overhead again.
请看投影仪
Well, in order to set this thing going,
该如何使用这个玩意儿呢？
I just want to show you some behavior out of this simulator.
我需要给你们说明下这个模拟器的用法
By the way, you may think this simulator is very simple,
你们可能觉得这个模拟器太简陋了
and probably too simple to be useful.
甚至你们认为它根本没什么用
The fact of the matter is
而实际上是
that this simulator has been used
这样的模拟器曾被用于
to manufacture a fairly large computer.
操纵相当大型的计算机
So this is a real live example.
那是一个真实的事例
Actually, not exactly this simulator，
当然 并不完全是这里的这个模拟器
because I'll tell you the difference.
我会告诉你它们的区别
The difference is that there were many more different kinds of primitives.
区别就是 操纵大型机的模拟器有更多的基本元素
There's not just the word inverter or and-gate.
不只是有非门 与门之类的
There were things like edge-triggered,
还有边缘触发器
flip-flops, and latches
翻转触发器 锁存器
transparent latches, and adders, and things like that.
电平触发器 加法器等等之类的
And the difficulty with that
困难之处在于
is there's pages and pages of the definitions of all these primitives
就在于需要很多页的文档
with numbers like LS04.
来描述这些基本元素
And then there's many more parameters for them.
同时它们还有很多的参数
It's not just one delay.
不是只有一个延时这么简单
There's things like set up times and hold times and all that.
还有建立时间 维持时间之类的
But with the exception of that part of the complexity,
但是 如果不算上那部分的复杂度
the structure of the simulator that we use for building a real computer,
我们用来构建真实计算机的模拟器的结构
that works is exactly what you're seeing here.
跟你们在这里看到的的是一致的
Well in any case, what we have here is a few simple things.
无论如何 这里都是一些简单的东西
Like, there's inverter delays being set up and making a new agenda.
像这个 设置非门的延时时间 构建一个 AGENDA
And then we can make some inputs.
我们可以构建一些输入（线路）
Ok? There's input-1, input-2, a sum and a carry, which are wires.
这里的四条线路分别是：INPUT-1、INPUT-2、SUM和CARRY
I'm going to put a special kind of object called a probe
我将要放置一种被称为“探针”的特殊对象
onto, onto some of the wires,
放在一些线路上
onto sum and onto carry.
放在SUM和CARRY上
A probe is a, can object that has the property
探针是一种对象 它可以 --
that when you change a wire it's attached to,
当你改变它所附着线路的信号时
it types out a message.
它会输出一条消息
It's an easy thing to do.
这很容易实现
And then once we have that,
一旦我们设置好它们
of course, then when you put the probe on,
当你在放置探针的时候
the first thing it does, it says,
它首先会输出
the current value of the sum at time 0 is 0
SUM在0时刻的值为0
And because I just noticed it.
这个我已经注意到了
And the value of the carry at time 0, this is the time, is 0.
CARRY在0时刻的值也是0
And then we go off and we build some structure.
我们继续来构建更多结构
Like, we can build a structure here that says
比如 可以像这里一样构建一种结构
you have a half-adder on input-1, input-2, sum, and carry.
用INPUT-1、INPUT-2、SUM和CARRY组成一个半加器
And we're going to set the signal on input-1 to 1.
然后我们把INPUT-1上的信号变为1
We do some propagation.
然后开始传播
At time 8,
在时刻8的时候
which you could see going through this thing if you wanted to,
如果你想的话 也可以单步跟踪传播过程
the new value of sum became 1.
SUM的值变为1
And the thing says I'm done.
然后就结束了
That wasn't very interesting.
好像没什么意思
But we can send it some more signals.
我们还可以设置信号
Like, we set-signal on input-2 to be one.
把INPUT-2也变为1
And at that time if we propagate,
如果再进行传播
then it carried at 11,
在时刻11
the carry becomes 1,
CARRY变为1
and at 16, the sum's new value becomes 0.
在时刻16 SUM变为0
And you might want to work out that, if you like, about the digital circuitry.
如果你仔细研究那个电路图
It's true, and it works.
它确实是这个结果
And it's not very interesting.
也并没有什么特别的
But that's the kind of behavior we get out of this thing.
但是却清楚地表明了这一些都是如何运作的
So what I've shown you right now
我现在给你们展示的是
is a large-scale picture,
一种宏观的图景
how you, at a bigger, big scale,
你如何在一个很大的规模中
you implement an event-driven simulation of some sort.
你何去实现某种事件驱动的模拟
And how you might organize it
你应该如何去组织
to have nice hierarchical structure
来获得良好的层次性结构
allowing you to build abstract boxes that you can instantiate.
使得你可以构建可具体化的抽象盒子
But I haven't told you any of the details about how this agenda and things like that work.
但我还没有告诉你AGENDA是如何运作的
That we'll do next.
下一小节再说
And that's going to involve change and mutation of data and things like that.
这将涉及到一些关于数据变化之类的事情
Are there any questions now, before I go on?
在我继续之前 有什么问题吗？
Thank you. Let's take a break.
没有的话 那就休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
计算对象
Well, we've been making a simulation.
我们已经做了一个模拟器
And the simulation is an event-driven simulation
这是一种事件驱动的模拟
where the objects in the world are the objects in the computer.
其中 计算机中的对象与现实中的对象一一对应
And the changes of state that are happening in the world in time
现实世界中按时发生的状态改变
are organized to be time in the computer,
被组织成了计算机中的时间
so that if something happens after something else in the world,
如果现实中某件事后于另一件事发生
then we have it happen after,
那么在计算机中
after the corresponding events happen in the same order in the computer.
两个事件也保持同样的先后顺序发生
That's where we have assignments, when we make that alignment.
排列这些时间 就是我们要用到赋值的地方
Right now I want to show you a way of organizing time,
现在我要介绍一种方法来组织时间
which is an agenda or priority queue, it's sometimes called.
AGENDA -- 或者有时候所谓的“优先队列”
We'll do some--we'll do a little bit of just understanding
我们首先需要认识到
what are the things we need to be able to do to make agendas.
为了创建AGENDA 我们需要些什么东西？
And so we're going to have--and so right now over here, I'm going to write down a bunch
首先我要在这里写下一些
of primitive operations for manipulating agendas.
用于操作AGENDA的基本运算
I'm not going to show you the code for them
我不会给出具体代码
because they're all very simple,
因为它们都非常简单
Iand you've got listings of all that anyway.
而且你们手上也有
So what do we have?
有哪些运算呢？
We have things like make-agenda which produces a new agenda.
MAKE-AGENDA可以新建一个AGENDA
We can ask--we get the current-time of an agenda,
CURRENT-TIME可以获得一个AGENDA的当前时间
of an agenda, which gives me a number, a time.
返回一个数 -- 也就是当前时间
We can get--we can ask whether an agenda is empty, empty-agenda.
EMPTY-AGENDA?可用于判断一个AGENDA是否为空
And that produces either a true or a false.
返回TRUE或FALSE
We can add an object to an agenda.
我们也可以向AGENDA中添加对象
Actually, what we add to an agenda is an operation--an action to be done.
实际上 向AGENDA中添加的是一个运算 -- 或者说是需要完成的操作
And that takes a time,
它需要时间TIME
the action itself,
待添加的动作ACTION
and the agenda I want to add it to.
以及AGENDA本身
OK? That inserts it in the appropriate place in the agenda.
它把ACTION 放入AGENDA中合适的地方
I can get the first item off an agenda,
FIRST-ITEM用于从AGENDA取出第一个事项
the first thing I have to do,
那是我首先需要做的事情
which is going to give me an action.
该事项是一个动作
And I can remove the first item from an agenda.
我还可以把第一个事项从AGENDA中移除
That's what I have to be able to do with agendas.
这是操作AGENDA的一个必要运算
That is a big complicated mess.
这个运算实现起来非常繁杂
From an agenda.
从AGENDA中移除
Well, let's see how we can organize this thing as a data structure a bit.
现在我们来看如何具体组织数据结构
Well, an agenda is going to be some kind of list.
AGENDA应该是一种表
And it's going to be a list that I'm going to have to be able to modify.
一种可修改的表
So we have to talk about modifying of lists,
因为我们要向其中添加元素
because I'm going to add things to it,
删除元素等等
and delete things from it, and things like that.
所以我们需要一种可修改的表
It's organized by time.
它通过时间组织起来
It's probably good to keep it in sorted order.
让它有序 也许会有益处
But sometimes there are lots of things that happen at the same time
但是也有可能同一时间会发生很多事
approximate same time.
或者说几乎同时
What I have to do is say,
因此我们需要
group things by the time at which they're supposed to happen.
把它们按发生时间为事件分组
So I'm going to make an agenda as a list of segments.
所以我要把AGENDA组织成由SEGMENT构成的表
And so I'm going to draw you a data structure for an agenda,
我来画一下这个结构
a perfectly reasonable one.
方便理解
Here's an agenda.
这是一个AGENDA
It's a thing that begins with a name.
以一个名字开始
I'm going to do it right now out of list structure.
我把它画在表结构的外部
It's got a header.
这是它的头部
There's a reason for the header.
这个头部的存在也是很必要的
We're going to see the reason soon.
待会你就会知道
And it will have a segment. We will have--
再画一个SEGMENT
It will have--it will be a list of segments.
这是一个由SEGMENT构成的表
Supposing this agenda has two segments,
假设这个AGENDA有两个SEGMENT
OK, they're the car's-- successive car's of this list.
不断对这个表取CAR即可得到
Each segment is going to have a time--
每个SEGMENT都有一个时间
say for example, 10--
比如说这里是10
that says that the things that happen in this segment are at time 10.
也就是说 这个SEGMENT里的事件发生在10时刻
And what I'm going to have in here is another data structure
这里是另外一种数据结构
which I'm not going to describe,
我先不具体描述
which is a queue of things to do at time 10.
它是一个队列 表示在10时刻要做的事
It's a queue.
它是一个队列
And we'll talk about that in a second.
一会儿再细说
But abstractly, the queue is just a list of things to do at a particular time.
不过抽象地看 队列就是一系列在固定时间要做的事
And I can add things to a queue.
我可以向其中添加其它要做的事
This is a queue.
这是一个队列
There's a time, there's a segment.
这个是时间 这个是SEGMENT
Now, I may have another segment in this agenda.
在这个AGENDA中 还有另一个SEGMENT
Supposing this is stuff that happens at time 30.
假设它在30时刻发生
It has, of course, another queue
类似地 它也有一个队列
of things that are queued up to be done at time 30.
里面是在30时刻要去做的事
Well, there are various things I have to be able to do to an agenda.
当然 我们的AGENDA还需要支持其它操作
Supposing I want to add to an agenda
假设我想将一个在10时刻发生的事
another thing to be done at time 10.
添加到AGENDA中
Well, that's not very hard.
这并不难
I'm going to walk down here, looking for the segment of time 10.
我遍历到这里 找到时刻是10的SEGMENT
It is possible that there is no segment of time 10.
这样的SEGMENT也可能不存在
We'll cover that case in a second.
一会儿再考虑这种情况
But if I find a segment of time 10,
如果我找到了时刻为10的SEGMENT
then if I want to add another thing to be done at time 10,
如果我想要把一个事情放入其中
I just increase that queue--
我只要增加该队列即可
"just increase" isn't such an obvious idea.
这个说起来倒是很容易
But I increase the things to be done at that time.
我在这里添加需要在那时做的事
Now, supposing I want to add something to be done at time 20.
现在 假设我想在时刻20做点什么
There is no segment for time 20.
然而并没有时刻是20的SEGMENT
I'm going to have to create a new segment.
我不得不构造一个新的SEGMENT
I want my time 20 segment to exist between time 10 and time 30.
我想把这个SEGMENT 放在10与30之间
Well, that takes a little work.
这着实要花点功夫
I'm going to have to do a CONS.
先用CONS
I'm going to have to make a new element of the agenda list--list of segments.
我要为这个AGENDA构建一个新的SEGMENT
I'm going to have to change.
这里的连接必须要变
Here's change.
就像这样
I'm going to have to change the CDR of the CDR of the agenda
我将要修改AGENDA的CDR部分的CDR部分
point that a new CONS of the new segment
让它指向一个新的CONS单元
and the CDR of the CDR of the CDR of the agenda, the CD-D-D-DR.
由一个新的SEGMENT和AGENDA的CDDDDR部分所构成的单元
And this is going to have a new segment now of time 20
我们有一个发生在20时刻的新的SEGMENT
with its own queue,
它自己维护了一个队列
which now has one element in it.
这个队列中只有一个元素
If I wanted to add something at the end,
如果我想在后面添加点什么
I'm going to have to replace the CDR of this,
我就需要替换这个东西的CDR部分
of this list with something.
替换掉这个表的CDR部分
We're have to change that piece of data structure.
我们就对该数据结构进行修改
So I'm going to need new primitives for doing this.
因此我需要新的基本运算
But I'm just showing you why I need them.
因为原有的基础运算达不到这一点
And finally, if I wanted to add a thing to be done at time 5,
如果我想在5时刻做点什么事
I'm going to have to change this one,
我就得去修改这个东西
because I'm going to have to add it in over here,
因为我得添加到这里
which is why I planned ahead and had a header cell,
这也就是我预留了一个“头”序对的原因
which has a place.
它预留了空间
If I'm going to change things, I have to have places for the change.
我需要有空间去做改变
I have to have a place to make the change.
需要有存储空间 去改变
If I remove things from the agenda, that's not so hard.
从AGENDA中删除东西并不困难
Removing them from the beginning is pretty easy,
移除第一个元素相当容易
which is the only case I have.
这也是我需要考虑的唯一情况
I can go looking for the first, the first segment.
我可以先找到第一个SEGMENT
I see if it has a non-empty queue.
先判断它的队列是否为空
If it has a non-empty queue,
如果队列不是空的
well, I'm going to delete one element from the queue
那么 我就会把元素从中删除
like that.
像这样
If the queue ever becomes empty,
如果这时队列变为空的
then I have to delete the whole segment.
就还要继续把SEGMENT删掉
And then this, this changes to point to here.
然后 让这个单元指向这里
So it's quite a complicated data structure manipulation going on,
这个数据结构操作起来很复杂
the details of which are not really very exciting.
它的具体实现也不是很有趣
Now, let's talk about queues.
现在我们来探讨一下队列
They're similar.
它们很相似
Because each of these agendas has a queue in it.
每一个AGENDA都有一个队列
What's a queue?
队列是什么？
A queue is going to have the following primitive operations.
队列能够进行下述基本运算：
To make a queue, this gives me a new queue.
MAKE-QUEUE构建一个新队列
I'm going to have to be able to insert into a queue a new item.
INSERT-QUEUE!向队列中插入新元素
I'm going to have to be able to delete from a queue the first item in the queue.
DELETE-QUEUE!从队列中删除元素
And I want to be able to get the first thing in the queue from some queue.
FRONT-QUEUE查看队列中第一个元素
I also have to be able to test whether a queue is empty.
还需要检测队列是否为空
And when you invent things like this,
当你定义像这样的运算时
I want you to be very careful
我希望你能够注意
to use the kinds of conventions I use for naming things.
按照我这样的习惯去为它们命名
Notice that I'm careful to say these change something and that tests it.
“!”表示操作具有副作用 “?”代表定义谓词
And presumably, I did the same thing over here.
就比如说 这里应该加上一个“!”
OK, and there should be an empty test over here.
嗯 空检测谓词的“?”也不要遗漏了
OK, well, how would I make a queue?
那么 我要如何构建一个队列呢？
A queue wants to be something I can add to at the end of,
队列是一种 可以向其尾部添加东西
and pick up the thing at the beginning of.
也可以从前面取出东西的结构
I should be able to delete from the beginning and add to the end.
我可以从队列头删除元素 向队列尾添加元素
Well, I'm going to show you a very simple structure for that.
我可以用一种很简单的结构来实现
We can make this out of CONSes as well.
我们当然可以使用CONS来构造
Here's a queue.
这是一个队列
It has--it has a queue header,
它有一个队列头
which contains two parts--
它包含两个部分
a front pointer
其中一个是头指针
and a rear pointer.
另一个是尾指针
And here I have a queue with two items in it.
假设我有一个包含两个元素的队列
The first item, I don't know, it's perhaps a 1.
假设第一个元素是1
And the second item, I don't know, let's give it a 2.
而第二个元素假定是2
The reason why I want two pointers in here,
我之所以要在这里设置两个指针
a front pointer and a rear pointer,
一个头指针和一个尾指针
is so I can add to the end
这样 当向尾部添加元素的时候
without having to chase down from the beginning.
就不用从最开始开始遍历
So for example, if I wanted to add one more item to this queue,
例如 我想要向队列添加入一个新元素
if I want to add on another item to be worried about later,
如果想添加一个稍后使用的元素
all I have to do is make a CONS,
只需要先用CONS构建一个序对
which contains that item, say a 3.
假设它包含一个值 -- 3
That's for inserting 3 into the queue.
再添加到队列里
Then I have to change this pointer here
这里就需要把这个元素CDR部分的指针
Okay? to here.
指向这个元素
And I have to change this one to point to the new rear.
同时也更新尾指针 让它指向新的地方
If I wish to take the first element of the queue, the first item,
如果我想查看队列的第一个元素
I just go chasing down the front pointer until I find the first one and pick it up.
我只需要通过头指针去寻找 即可轻松找到
If I wish to delete the first item from the queue, delete-queue,
如果我想调用DELETE-QUEUE删除元素
all I do is move the front pointer along this way.
只需要把头指针向后移到就行
The new front of the queue is now this.
新的头指针指向这里
So queues are very simple too.
就是这么简单
So what you see now
为了实现这些操作
is that I need a certain number of new primitive operations.
我们还需要一些新的基本运算
And I'm going to give them some names.
我先列出它们的名字
And then we're going to look into how they work, and how they're used.
然后我们再来看 它们的原理和使用方法
We have set the CAR of some pair,
SET-CAR!能够为序对的CAR部分
or a thing produced by CONSing, to a new value.
赋予一个新的值
And set the CDR of a pair to a new value.
SET-CDR!可以为序对的CDR部分赋新值
And then we're going to look into how they work.
现在来看看它们到底做了什么
I needed setting CAR over here to delete the first element of the queue.
为了删除队列中的第一个元素 我需要修改这里的CAR部分
This is the CAR, and I had to set it.
这是CAR部分 我需要修改它的值
I had to be able to set the CDR
我需要能够修改CDR部分
to be able to move the rear pointer,
以便我能够移动尾指针
or to be able to increment the queue here.
也使得我能够扩充队列
All of the operations I did
之前介绍的所有运算
were made out of those that I just showed you on the, on the last blackboard.
上一块黑板上的所有东西 都是基于这些运算的
Good. Let's pause the time, and take a little break then.
先讲到这里 大家休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
计算对象
When we originally introduced pairs made out of CONS, made by CONS,
最初 我们说序对是通过CONS构造而来的
we only said a few axioms about them,
我们提到了几条公理
which were of the form-- what were they--
它们是怎样的呢？ 它们是形如 --
for all X and Y, the CAR of the CONS of X and Y is X
对于任意的X和Y (CAR (CONS X Y)) = X
and Y is X and the CDR of the CONS of X and Y is Y.
以及 (CDR (CONS X Y)) = Y
Now, these say nothing about whether a CONS has an identity like a person.
但是 它们并没有陈述CONS单元 是否有像人一样的“身份”
In fact, all they say is something sort of abstract,
实际上 它描述的是一种抽象
that a CONS is the parts it's made out of.
也就是CONS是由几个部分组成
And of course, two things are made out of the same parts, they're the same,
如果两个CONS组成部分相同的  它俩则是同样的
at least from the point of view of these axioms.
至少从这些公理来看是这样的
But by introducing assignment--
但是引入了赋值以后
in fact, mutable data is a kind of assignment,
实际上 可变数据就是一种赋值
we have a set CAR and a set CDR--
我们有SET-CAR!和SET-CDR!
by introducing those, these axioms no longer tell the whole story.
引入这些运算后 这些公理就不完整了
And they're still true if written exactly like this.
但是这里写的也是对的
But they don't tell the whole story.
只不过描述的不再完整
Because if I'm going to set a particular CAR in a particular CONS,
因为如果我要修改一个特定的CONS的CAR部分
the questions are,
问题是
well, is that setting all CARs and all CONSes of the same two things or not?
我会同时修改到相同CONS单元的CAR部分么？
If I--if we use CONSes to make up things like rational numbers,
假如我用CONS来构建有理数
or things like 3 over 4,
比如说3/4
supposing I had two three-fourths.
假设我有两个3/4
Are they the same one--
这两个一样吗？
or are they different?
或者又不一样？
Well, in the case of numbers, it doesn't matter.
当然 对于数字来说 这并不重要
Because there's no meaning to changing the denominator of a number.
修改一个数的分母并没有数学意义
What you could do is make a number which has a different denominator.
我们只能够说创建一个数 具有不同的分母
But the concept of changing a number which has to have a different denominator
而直接修改一个数的分母这种观念
is sort of a very weird, and sort of not supported by what you think of as mathematics.
在数学意义上是一种非常奇怪而不受支持的行为
However, when these CONSes represent things in the physical world,
然而 当这些CONS单元表示的是现实世界中的事物
then changing something like the CAR
那么修改它的CAR部分
like removing a piece of the fingernail.
就像除掉指甲壳的一块一样
And so CONSes have an identity.
所以 每一个CONS都有自己的“身份”
Let me show you what I mean about identity, first of all.
我来先说明“身份”是什么意思
Let's do some little example here.
来看些例子
Supposing I define A to the CONS of 1 and 2.
假如(DEFINE A (CONS 1 2))
Well, what that means, first of all,
这是代表什么呢？ 首先
is that somewhere in some environment I've made a symbol A
这是说我在某个环境中创建了符号A
to have a value which is a pair
而它的值是一个序对
consisting of pointers to a 1 and a pointer to a 2,
这个序对由两个分别指向1和2的指针组成
just like that.
就像这样
Now, supposing I also say
又假设
define B to be the CONS--
(DEFINE B (CONS A A))
it doesn't matter, but I like it better, it's prettier--
虽然无所谓 不过我还是更喜欢用大写
of A and A.
(DEFINE B (CONS A A))
Well, first of all, I'm using the name A twice.
这里用了两次A
At this moment, I'm going to think of CONSes as having identity.
现在就要考虑序对的身份问题了
This is the same one.
这两个A是同一个东西
And so what that means
这也就是说
is I make another pair,
我创建了另一个序对
which I'm going to call B.
我把它记作B
And it contains two pointers to A.
它由两个指向A的指针组成
At this point, I have three names for this object.
对于这个对象来说 此时我有三个名字来指称它
A is its name.
A是一个
The CAR of B is its name.
(CAR B)是一个
And the CDR of B is its name.
(CDR B)也是一个
It has several aliases, they're called.
都是这个序对的别名
Now, supposing I do something like set-the-CAR,
假设现在我要执行
the CAR of the CAR of B to 3.
(SET-CAR! (CAR B) 3)
What that means is I find the CAR of B, that's this.
我先去找B的CAR部分 也就是它
I set the CAR of that to be 3, changing this.
再修改它的CAR部分 修改为3
I've changed A.
这样我也就修改了A
If I were to ask what's the CAR of A--of A now?
如果我问 现在A的CAR部分是多少
I would get out 3,
结果是3
even though here we see that A was the CONS of 1 and 2.
尽管在这里 A是由1和2构成的序对
I caused A to change by changing B.
我通过改变B而改变了A
There is sharing here.
它们之间存在共享
That's sometimes what we want.
有时候我们需要这样的结构
Surely in the queues and things like that,
当然 在类似于队列这类的数据结构中
that's exactly what we defined our--organized our data structures to facilitate-- sharing.
我们正是这样来定义、组织数据结果来获得数据共享的
But inadvertent sharing,
但是有一些非预期的共享
unanticipated interactions between objects,
对象间的非预期交互
is the source of most of the bugs that occur in complicated programs.
是大型程序中产生的BUG的主要来源
So by introducing this possibility of things having identity and sharing
通过使对象具有“身份”、允许共享
and having multiple names for the same thing,
给同一个对象取多个别名
we get a lot of power.
我们获得了强大的能力
But we're going to pay for it with lots of complexity and bugs.
但是同时也为此引出的BUG和复杂度而付出代价
So also, for example, if I just looked at this just to drive that home,
为了把这个讲透彻一点 我们再举一个例子
the CADR of B,
比如(CADR B)
which has nothing to do with even the CAR of B, apparently.
看起来和(CAR B)没有一点关系
The CADR of B, what's that?
但是它的值是什么？
Take that CDR of B and now take the CAR of that.
先取B的CDR部分 再取结果的CAR部分
Oh, that's 3 also.
哦 还是3
So I can have non-local interactions by sharing.
有了共享这样的机制 局部的含义也不是那么清楚了
And I have to be very careful of that.
所以我们要非常小心的操作
Well, so far, of course, it seems I've introduced several different assignment operators--
目前为止 我已经介绍了好几个赋值运算
set, set CAR, set CDR.
比如SET!、SET-CAR!、SET-CDR!
Well, maybe I should just get rid of set CAR and set CDR. Maybe they're not worthwhile.
或许我应该不用SET-CAR!、SET-CDR! 它们引入太多问题了
Well, the answer is
而事实则是
that once you let the camel's nose into the tent,
一旦把骆驼的鼻子牵进帐篷
the rest of him follows.
它的身体可就自己跟进来了
All I have to have is set,
只要有SET!
and I can make all of the--all of the bad things that can happen.
这些糟糕的东西都可能发生
Let's play with that a little bit.
我们来分析一下
A couple of days ago, when we introduced compound data,
前些日子 讲到复合数据的时候
you saw Hal show you a definition of CONS in terms of a message acceptor.
哈罗德教授向你们展示了 用消息接收的方式来定义CONS
I'm going to show you even a more horrible thing,
我将给你们展示一种更加糟糕的方式
a definition of CONS in terms of nothing but air,
凭“空”定义CONS
hot air.
“什么”都不用
What is the definition of CONS, of the old functional kind,
用传统的函数式的方法如何定义CONS呢？
in terms of purely lambdic expressions,
纯粹只用LAMBDA表达式
procedures?
把序对表示成过程
Because I'm going to then modify this definition
现在我要修改这个定义
to get assignment to be only one kind of assignment,
使得只具有一种赋值
to get rid of the set CAR and set CDR in terms of set.
用SET!来代替SET-CAR!和SET-CDR!
So what if I define CONS of X and Y
如果我把CONS定义为
to be a procedure of one argument called a message M,
定义为一个过程 该过程接收参数M
which calls that message on X and Y?
该过程将M应用在X与Y上
This idea was invented by Alonzo Church,
这是阿隆佐·丘奇发明的方法
who was the greatest programmer of the 20th century,
他是20世纪最伟大的程序员
although he never saw a computer.
尽管当时电脑还没有被发明
It was done in the 1930s.
但他在20世纪30年代就提出了这个方法
He was a logician, I suppose at Princeton at the time.
他是一个逻辑学家 在普林斯顿大学做研究
Define CAR of X
定义(CAR X)为
to be the result of applying X to that procedure of two arguments,
把X应用在一个二元过程上
A and D, which selects A.
参数分别是A和D 而结果是选出A
I will define CDR of X
而(CDR X)则是
to be that procedure,
这样的一个过程
to be the result of applying X to that procedure of A and D,
把X应用在一个参数分别是A和D的过程上
which selects D.
该过程选择出D
Now, you may not recognize this as CAR, CDR, and CONS.
可能你们还没意识到这些就是CAR、CDR和CONS
But I'm going to demonstrate to you that it satisfies the original axioms
但我将要给你们演示它符合之前的公理
just once.
举一个例子
And then we're going to do some playing of games.
我们来看一下
Consider the problem CAR of CONS of, say, 35 and 47.
考虑一下语句语句(CAR (CONS 35 47))
Well, what is that?
它的结果是多少呢？
It is the result of taking car of the result of substituting 35 and 47
它是通过把35和47代换进
X and Y in the body of this.
语句体中的X和Y得到的
Well, that's easy enough.
非常容易
That's CAR of the result of substituting into lambda of M, M of 35 and 47.
就得到了语句(CAR (LAMBDA (M) (M 35 47)))
Well, what this is, is the result of substituting this object
这个的结果是把这个对象
for X in the body of that.
代换进这里的X而得到的
So that's just lambda of M--
代换的结果是((LAMBDA (M --
that's substituted, because this object is being substituted for X,
用这个对象代换这里的X
which is the beginning of a list,
这是表的头部
lambda of M-- M of 35 and 47,
体的部分是(M 35 47)
applied to that procedure of A and D,
把它应用于一个参数分别的A和D的过程上
which gives me A.
后者返回参数A
Well, that's the result of substituting this for M here.
然后我们用这个来代换这里的M
So that's the same thing as lambda of A, D, A,
这个就相当于把(LAMBDA (A D) A)
applied to 35 and 47.
应用在35和47上
Oh, well that's 35.
结果就是35
That's substituting 35 for A and for 47 for D in A.
它就是用35和47分别代换A、D 最后返回A
So I don't need any data at all.
所以我根本不需要任何数据
not even numbers.
甚至连数字都不需要
This is Alonso Church's hack.
这就是 阿隆佐·邱奇的技巧
Well, now we're going to do something nasty to him.
现在呢我们来对这个定义做点修改
Being a logician, he wouldn't like this.
作为逻辑学家 他可能会不太开心
But as programmers, let's look at the overhead.
但作为程序员 -- 请看投影仪
And here we go.
我们来看看
I'm going to change the definition of CONS.
我修改了CONS的定义
It's almost the same as Alonzo Church's, but not quite.
和丘奇的定义很相似 但是不完全相同
What do we have here?
具体到底是什么？
The CONS of two arguments, X and Y,
CONS有两个参数：X和Y
is going to be that procedure of one argument M,
但它返回一个参数为M的过程
which supplies M to X and Y as before,
跟之前一样M会应用于X和Y上
but also to two permissions,
但它额外还有两个“许可”
the permission to set X to N
其中一个是把X赋值为N
and the permission to set Y to N,
另一个则是把Y赋值为N
given that I have an N.
只要我提供了相应的N
So besides the things that I had here in Church's definition,
所以出了邱奇原本的定义之外
what I have is that the thing that CONS returns
最大的不同在于CONS的返回值
will apply its argument
不单会把它的参数应用于
to not just the values of the X and Y that the CONS is made of,
用于构成序对的X和Y之上
but also permissions to set X and Y to new values.
它还有用于为X和Y赋值的两个“许可”
Now, of course, just as before,
当然 就如之前一样
CAR is exactly the same.
CAR看起来也很相似
The CAR of X is nothing more than applying X,
就像邱奇定义的那样
as in Church's definition,
(CAR X)只不过是把X应用在
to a procedure, in this case, of four arguments,
过程上 -- 本例中是四个参数
which selects out the first one.
然后从中选出第一个
And just as we did before,
这就和之前一样
that will be the value of X
结果将会返回X
that was contained in the procedure which is the result of evaluating this lambda expression
X的值被包含在求值这个LAMBDA表达式所产生的过程中
in the environment where X and Y are defined over here.
X和Y的值也是在这个环境中定义的
That's the value of CONS.
这是我们对CONS的定义
Now, however, the exciting part.
那么 激动人心的地方来了
CDR, of course, is the same.
当然CDR的定义也类似
The exciting part,
激动人心的地方
set CAR and set CDR.
SET-CAR!和SET-CDR!的实现
Well, they're nothing very complicated anymore.
说实话 它们也不是特别复杂
Set CAR of a CONS X to a new value Y
语句(SET-CAR! X Y)
is nothing more than applying that CONS,
无非就是把序对X应用于
which is the procedure of four--the procedure of one argument
注意X是一个一元过程
which applies its argument to four things,
该过程的体是将参数应用在四个对象上
to a procedure which is of four arguments--
我们把X应用于一个四元过程上
the value of X, the value of Y,
X的值、Y的值
permission to set X, the permission to set Y--
修改X的许可、修改Y的许可
and using it--using that permission to set X to the new value.
语句的体则是用相应的许可 将X设置为新的值
And similarly, set-cdr is the same thing.
当然SET-CDR!和它类似
So what you've just seen is that I didn't introduce any new primitives at all.
你也看到了 我这里并没有引入新的基本运算
I mean, Whether or not I want to implement it this way is a matter of engineering.
具体要不要这样来实现是一个工程性问题
And the answer is of course I don't implement it this way
当然出于工程上的考量
for reasons that have to do with engineering.
我不会这样来实现
However in principle, logically,
但是从原理上来说
I introduced one assignment operator,
一旦引入了赋值运算
I've assigned--I've introduced them all.
我就可以进行各种各样的赋值运算了
Are there any questions?
有什么问题吗？
Yes, David.
请讲
AUDIENCE: I can follow you up until you get--I can follow all of that.
我可以跟的上你的思路 直到 --
But when we bring in the permissions,
在许可那里
defining CONS in terms of the lambda N,
我们把CONS定义为一个参数为N的过程
I don't follow where N gets passed.
我不知道这个参数是什么时候传进来的
PROFESSOR: Oh, I'm sorry. I'll show you.
教授：哦 抱歉 我给你演示一下
Let's follow it.
我们来推演一下
Of course, we could do it on the blackboard.
虽然在黑板上推演更清晰
It's not so hard.
但这并不难懂
But it's also easy here.
我就将就用投影仪了
Supposing I wish to set-cdr of X to Y.
调用(SET-CDR! X Y)会发生什么呢？
See that right there. set cdr x to y
就在这里(SET-CDR! X Y)
X is presumably a CONS,
X可能是一个序对
a thing resulting from evaluating CONS.
或者说对一个CONS表达式求值得到的结果
right?
能跟上吧？
Therefore X comes from a place over here,
也就是说 X是由这里的代码构造出来的
that that X is of the result of evaluating this lambda expression.
这里的X是求值这个LAMBDA表达式得到的
Right?
对吧
That when I evaluated that lambda expression,
因此当我对这个LAMBDA表达式求值时
I evaluated it in an environment where the arguments to CONS were defined.
我是在定义CONS时的一个环境里求值的
That means that as free variables in this lambda expression,
这也就是说 作为LAMBDA表达式中的自由变量
there is the--there are in the frame,
X和Y都存储一个框架中
which is the parent frame of this lambda expression,
也就是这整个LAMBDA表达式的父框架
the procedure resulting from this lambda expression,
因此在这个LAMBDA语句中
X and Y have places.
X和Y都有存储空间
And it's possible to set them.
也可以对它们赋值
I set them to an N, which is the argument of the permission.
这里赋值为N是通过参数来传递的
The permission is a procedure
“许可”就是一个过程
which is passed to M,
它将作为M的一个参数
which is the argument that the CONS object gets passed.
它实际上是CONS生成的对象的一部分
Now, let's go back here in the set-cdr
我们再来看看SET-CDR!
The CONS object, which is the first argument of set-cdr
SET-CDR!的第一个参数X是一个序对
gets passed an argument.
被传递了一个参数
That--there's a procedure of four things, indeed,
这个是一个四元过程
because that's the same thing as this M over here,
这是因为 它要作为这里的M
which is applied to four objects.
要应用在四个对象上
The object over here, SD, is, in fact, this permission.
这边的这个SD 就对应于这个过程
When I use SD, I apply it to Y, right there.
当我执行SD 把它应用于Y
So that comes from this.
这个Y是这里传过来的
AUDIENCE: So what do you--
学生：那--
PROFESSOR: So to finish that, the N that was here is the Y which is here.
教授：所以说 这里的N就对应于这里的Y
How's that?
明白了吧
AUDIENCE: Right, OK.
了解了
Now, when you do a set-cdr,
当你执行SET-CDR!的时候
X is the value the CDR is going to become.
X是CDR部分要赋值的新值
PROFESSOR: The X over here.
教授：这里的X
I'm sorry, that's not true.
哦 指错了
The X is--set-cdr has two arguments--
这里的X是指 -- SET-CDR!有两个参数
The CONS I'm changing
一个是被修改的序对
and the value I'm changing it to.
还有就是新值
So you have them backwards, that's all.
你可以代换回去看看 就很清楚了
Are there any other questions?
还有什么问题吗？
Well, thank you.
好的
It's time for lunch.
这节课就到这里
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP